Well, well, that's it Well, what can I say Well,
Ну ну вот что Ну что я могу сказать Ну
I know that a teacher's salary in
зарплата у учителя я знаю в
Buryatia is 25,000, the average salary, and from
Бурятии там 25.000 средняя зарплата и из
that you have to pay personal income tax, they
них ты должен заплатить НДФЛ его ещё
raised it this year, and from that you have to
подняли в этом году из них ты должен
pay utilities if
заплатить коммунальные услуги если у
you have a child You also have to Well, if he's
тебя ребёнок Ты должен ещё Ну если он
naturally small, there's a small one, there's
естественно маленький там небольшой там
a sixteen-year-old, there's a seventeen-year-old,
шестнадцатилетний там семнадцатилетний
well, that is, he can't
ну то есть работать не может
go to work, you still have to support him, but you
пойти ты ещ его должен содержать но на
can't survive on that salary No matter how hard you
эту зарплату не выжить Как бы ты не
try That's why you get out loans,
старался Поэтому ты вылезаешь кредиты
debts, a
долги в
mortgage
ипотеку
Great Hello Hello Where are you from I'm from
Здорово Привет Привет Ты откуда Я из
Russia Yes, I can see from the situation
России Да я вижу по обстановке город
what kind of city Ulan-Ud
какой улану уд
Buryatia Yes, in short, my dad served in Chita Ugu
Бурятия Да у меня короче там в Чите вну
Cool Are you a Buryat or a
батя служил Угу Прикольно А ты бурят или
Russian Ukrainian, who am I, a Chuvash, a Chuvash,
русский украинец кто я чуваш чуваш
cool, and
прикольно и
Cheboksary No, just from the Chuvash Well, a
Чебоксар Нет продом просто из чувашей Ну
deep Chuvash village on the ear, how did you get to Buryatia Well, I
глубокая Чувашская деревня по ухой как в
left to serve, I met a girl,
попал Ну служить уехал с девушкой
I decided to stay in Buryatia,
познакомился решил остаться в буряти
the girl is a Buryat  Chuvash No, Russian, I
девушка бурятка чувашка Нет русская
understand, well, a
понял ну
crossbreed And now who will your children be? Probably mestizos, and by nationality Well,
метисы наверно а по национальности Ну
if I am Chuvash, she is a mixture of Russian, Russian, and
если я чуваш она поме рус русского и
Buryat, a vinaigrette, then Chuvash is a Russian
бурята винегрет то тогда чуваш русский
storm, some kind of storm,
буря какой-то
in fact Yes, in fact Yes, well, just
получа по факту Да по факту Да ну просто
If we judge As Jews, then it will be boom,
Если судить Как евреи то он будет бумм
Russian
русским
storms, yours understood Listen, what do you think
бурям ваш понял Слушай а как ты
about the fact that Russia is now at war
относишься к тому что сейчас Россия воют
with
с
Ukraine, in general, it is bad in fact And
Украиной вообще плохо на самом деле А
what do you think Why did all the
как считаешь Почему во началась все
wars start? It is bad Why did the war
войны Это плохо Почему почему война
start because they did not share something I
началась потому что не поделили что-то Я
do not know what they did not share Well, what they did not
не знаю что не поделили Ну что не
share I honestly do not know what they did not
поделили Я честно я не знаю что не
share, they could not
поделили могли не
share, for example, the
поделить например
parish, no division of
прихо вообще ни одна делёжка
human lives is worth it at all And what do you
человеческих жизней не стоит а как
think, who is to blame for the fact that this war is going on? The
считаешь кто виноват в том что идёт эта
Soviet
война Советский
Union has been gone for a long time now It is
Союз его уже давным-давно нету Именно
his policy that is the cause of the collapse that is to blame for
его политика причины распада виновата в
the fact that now, don’t look,
том то что сейчас вот не смотри виноваты
some specific people are always to blame
всегда какие-то люди
Well, in that case, Gorbachev
конкретные Ну в таком случае Горбачёв
Yeltsin Gorbachev is to blame for Putin attacking
Ельцин Горбач виноват что Путин напал на
Ukraine Gorbachev Yeltsin is to blame in general for
Украину Горбачёв Ельцин виноваты вообще
what happened in principle That's how
то что в принципе случилось Вот так
the nineties happened They were in all the republics were
девяностые Они во всех республиках были
n't they Look again specifically Putin
не так ли ещё раз смотри конкретно Путин
attacked
напал на
Ukraine Why is it not Putin who is to blame for this but
Украину Почему виноват в этом не Путин а
some piece
какой-то
of [ __ ] did not attack Ukraine and he did not
[__] не нападал на Украину а он не
attack Ukraine but in the consequences As let's
нападал на Украину но в последствия Как
say of his rule Here they are visible Already
скажем его правления Вот они видны Уже
clearly visible Look who made the
прекрасно видны Смотри кто принял
decision to attack Ukraine Vladimir
решение напасть на Украину Владимир
Vladimirovich then that means he is to
Владимирович то значит он
blame
виноват
Well I wouldn't say that he is to blame well
Ну не сказал бы что он виноват ну
wait Who did this de Well it's just it's just well
подожди Кто сделал это де Ну это просто
it's just a bubble once again
это просто ну это просто пузырь ещё раз
who did this action Vladimir
кто сделал это действие Владимир
Vladimirovich Well then it means he is to blame The
Владимирович Ну значит он виноват
Ministry of Defense then well Putin is
Министерство обороны значит ну Путин
to blame he signed this decree Well he
виноват он подписал этот указ Ну он
signed a decree on it turns out to be conducting a
подписал указ о получается проведение
special military operation That's how he
специальной военной операции Вот как он
said
сказал
that is he is
вот то есть он
to blame in principle it is to blame in general the
виноват в принципе виновато вообще вот
Soviet Union is to blame no once again look
Советский Союз виноват нет ещ раз смотри
the one who
виноват тот кто
did it is to blame and the one who is mean to it is not to blame
сделал а тот кто к этому подл не виноват
look the Soviet Union a long time ago
тот смотри Советского Союза давным-давно
No there are independent states
Нет есть независимые государство
attacked because something sometime
напал потому что что-то когда-то
Soviet Union yes Well I'm
Советский Союз да Ну я же
saying the bubble inflated and burst just once
говорю пузырь надулся и лопнул просто ещ
again the bubble
раз пузырь
inflated said the bubble inflated and will burst
надулся сказал пузырь надулся и лопну
specifically that
конкретне что
young already
молодых уже
old such that everything
старых такая вотк этому к этому всё
led to this everything
подводило к этому всё
led to this So let's look again
подводило Так давай ещё раз смотри
Soviet Union Yes
Советский Союз Да распался
15 countries collapsed everyone lived each their own way
15 стран все жили каждый своей дорогой
Yes you are a young country there Ukraine is a
Да вот вы молодая страна там Украина
young country Kazakhstan is a young country
молодая страна Казахстан молодая страна
why did Putin decide to attack
почему Путин решил напасть на
Ukraine I'm a speech
Украину Я же говор
that was not decided yet then what kind of
который не решили ещё тогда что за
unresolved question how do I know wait
нерешённый вопрос откуда я знаю подожди
So if you don't know then Why do you
Так если ты не знаешь то Зачем ты
open your mouth so clearly Well
открываешь рот так утверждаешь чётко Ну
because the Soviet Union is wait
потому что Советский Союз - это подожди
stop So you open your mouth and
стоп Значит ты открываешь рот и
assert something And when they clarify
утверждаешь что-то А когда тебя уточняют
you you say I don't know yes then you don't know
ты говоришь я не знаю да то ты не знаешь
or you know everything is correct if you don't
или ты знаешь всё верно если ты не
know why do you then open your mouth and
знаешь зачем ты тогда открываешь рот и
say ko
говоришь ко
mozhno what was divided in the Soviet Union
могу зна что поделили в Советском Союз
How do you know that it was the Soviet Union
Откуда ты знаешь что это Советский Союз
at all during the World Cup here well because politics
вообще при ЧМ тут ну потому что политика
it was visible What kind of vi So you don't
она была видна Какая ви Так ты же не
know how it is there This bubble
знаешь как там Пузырь этот
was called what was this bubble called I
назывался как этот пузырь назывался я
can know how this bubble inflated
могу знать как этот пузырь навал надулся
you say that something is going on there Yes but you do
ты же говоришь что там что-то идёт Да но
n't know what are you or what
не знаешь что ты какой-то что ли или что
I can't
я не могу
understand And so explain to me what happened in the
понять А так объясни мне что случи в
Soviet Union that the mountains are to blame
Советском Союзе такое что гор виноват
Tom Putin attacked Ukraine Well,
Том Путин напал на Украину А ну делёжка
at least the division of territory What division of
территории по крайней мере Какая делёжка
territory look at the Russian Federation
территории смотри у Российской Федерации
One One one country it turns out don't
Одна Одна одна получается страна не
look in the Soviet Union there were 15
смотри в Советском Союзе было 15
republics 15 republics one country was a
республик 15 республик одна страна была
whole Soviet Union [ __ ] was a
целая Советский Союз сри было
state Yes there were other states in it
государство Да в нём были другие
15 different states it
государства 15 разных государств он
Ukraine Ukraine for example in it was
Украина Украина например в он входила
even a part of the Soviet Union and there
даже и в состав Советский Союз и вон
was a Soviet Union - it's like the European Union
входил Советский Союз - это как Евросоюз
there were different States and a superstructure
там были разные Государство и надстройка
Yes, here is a state They decided to live
была Да вот государство Решили жить
separately Russia lived separately Ukraine
отдельно Россия жила отдельно Украина
lived separately Belarus And so on Yes and there
жила отдельно Белорусь И так дальше Да и
were no complaints Well wait
Никаких претензий не было Ну подожди
wait how can the Soviet Union be
стой как это вот Советский Союз можно
compared with NATO not with NATO with the European
сравнить с НАТО не с НАТО с Европейский
SS so Well look in the European Union
СС так Ну смотри в Европейском союзе
there are countries and there is the Council of Europe there is the
есть страны и есть совет Европы есть
European Union in it  different
Европейский союз в него входят разные
countries are included have the same currency as well as the
страны имеют одинаковую валюту так же и
Soviet Union these are different countries were well the
Советский Союз это разные страны были ну
capital of the European Union What is
столица Евросоюза Какая Брюссель
Brussels Brussels and what and there The most important
Брюссель и что и там Самый главный
person sits yes the European Union The most important
человек сидит да Евросоюза Самый главный
person of the European Union yes that is
человек Евросоюза да то есть у
Germany does not have a chancellor in fact and in
Германии нет канцлера по факту и в
Germany there is a chancellor as well as in the
Германии есть канцлер так же как и в в
republics look Yeltsin was
республиках смотри Ельцин был
Uh the head of the RSFSR RFU Yes and the Union had its
Ээ главой РСФСР РФС Да а у Союза был
own head each Republic had its own
свой глава у каждой Республики свой
head as the head of state was so
глава как глава государства был так
When Yeltsin was already the
Когда Ельцин был уже же не существовал у
Soviet Union did not exist Are you kidding
советского Союз Ты что прикалываешься
Yeltsin still in the Soviet Union headed
Ельцин ещё в Советском Союзе возглавил
the RSFSR,
РСФСР
right Well yes in the ninetieth year in the
разве Ну да он в девяностом году в
ninetieth year he still proclaimed this
девяностом году ещё провозглашал это
declaration on the state
декларацию про государственный
sovereignty of the RSFSR
суверенитет РСФСР
Yeah And who And who was the head of Ukraine then
Угу А кто А кто главой был Украины тогда
Kravchuk Kravchuk before Kravchuk there were also
Кравчук Кравчук до кравчука там ещё были
these
эти
and
и
like Shcherby and
как Щербы ещё там
others In short it is clear how it is like the
другие Короче понятно как это как
European Union Well well so now you have the
Евросоюз Да ну так же у вас сейчас
Russian Federation as  The European Union
Российская Федерация как Евросоюз в неё
includes different states, for example,
входят разные государства например
Tatarstan, Bashkortostan,
Татарстан башкартастан
that Tatarstan is a state. Yes,
что Татарстан - это государство Да
take this right now, look,
возьми вот прямо сейчас смотри вот
take this on Google, the Constitution of
сейчас возьми этот на Гугле Конституция
the Republic of Tatarstan, and you will see that in the
Республики Татарстан и посмотришь в
first article it is written that it is a
первой статье написано что это
state. The Sakha Republic, it is written in the
государство Республика Саха написано в
first article that it is a state.
статье первой что государство
Read. You do not read your documents
Почитай Вы же не читаете свои документы
even for the sake of interest. Let me also write a
даже ради интереса Давай я тоже
democratic, democratic,
демократического демократическое
legal state of the Russian
правового государство Российской
Federation. Yes, just like Poland, a
Федерации Да так же как Польша
state within the European
государство в составе Европейского
Union. You see, Tatarstan is a state, it
Союза видишь Татарстан государство
is written, the truth is,
написано правда
the public
публики
Sakha is the same thing, it is written in the first article, a
Саха тоже самое написано в первой статье
state within the Constitution of
государство в составе Конституцию
Bashkortostan. Yes, the same thing is written, a
Башкортостана открыл Дава тоже самое
legal, democratic state, a
правовое демократическое государство
state. Imagine, all the Republics you have.
государство Прикинь все Республики у вас
Yes, they are separate
Да это отдельные
states. I did not make this up. You
государство Я же не придумал ты это
read it yourself too. Well, yes, of course, that is, the
прочитал сам тоже Ну да коне то есть
modern Russian Federation is the
современная Российская Федерация это
same as the European Union. There is
также как Евросоюз вход разе года там
Poland, Germany, they are part of the
Польша Германия они в составе
European Union. Yeah. And with you, that
Европейского Союза Угу Так и у вас то
is, you want to now lead to the fact
есть ты хочешь сейчас подвести к тому То
that, like, Russia as such does
что типа как таковой России Ну как
not exist. Well, as a country, or what is Russian
страны не существует или что российской
with you. Look, Russia is a Federation of
у вас Смотри Россия - это Федерация
different countries of different countries, just like the
разных стран разных стран так же как и
European Union.  Yeah, you came out in the second
Европейский союз Угу выш в дено втором
year, yes, all these countries signed the
году да подписали эти все страны
Federal Treaty Well, I know that yes, yes,
Федеративный договор Ну это я знаю да да
that is, you see, well, you just found out
то есть видишь ну ты только что узнал
that Tatarstan is the state of Bashkortostan, the state of
что Татарстан государство башкартастан
Buryatia, the state and so
государство Бурятия Государство и так
on, you live in the state of Buryatia,
дальше ты живёшь в государстве Бурятии
which is part of Well, look again at
которое входит Да ну посмотри ещё раз
the Constitution of Buryatia, the same thing will happen,
Конституцию буряти тоже самое будет это
it just sounds
это просто звучит
somehow just look at these states, as well
как-то просто смотри эти государства так
as, for example, the state of the European Union,
же как например государство Евросоюза
its powers, as well as your
своих полномочий также и ваше
state of Buryatia,
государства Бурятия
delegated According to the Federal
делегированное Согласно Федерального
Treaty of the ninety-second
договора девяносто второго
year, well, count the Constitution of Buryatia Well,
года ну посчитай Конституцию буряти Ну
here is the Constitution of Buryatia, ninety, whose
вот Конституция Бурятии девяносто чей
year, the first, the first article, yes, yes, yes, now a
год перва первая статья дадада сейчас
republic is opening Well, the same thing
открывается республика Ну тоже самое
is written, and what does the word Federation mean
написано а что означает слово Федерация
if
если
in Russian Well, honestly, I won’t say,
по-русски Ну честно не скажу
google Federation in Russian, the
загугли Федерация по-русски
translation will now be for you Revelation, a
перевод сейчас для тебя будет Откровение
state consisting of those united
государство состоящее из объединившихся
into a single state, not the word
в единое государственное не само слово
Federation itself Well, here is the
Федерация Ну вот
Federation now the Union of individual
Федерация сейчас Союз отдельных об
organizations, the Union, you see, the Union of the federation,
организаций Союз видишь Союз федера
translation Russian is the Union, that is, the European
перевод рус это союз то есть Европейский
Union and the Russian  Federation Russian
союз и Российская Федерация Российская
Federation is Russian
Федерация - это Российский
Union simply What is the difference between Russian
союз просто Чем отличается Российская
Federation and European Union Yes
Федерация от Европейского Союза Да
that Russian
что Российская
Federation countries included in Russian
Федерация страны входящие в Российскую
Federation gave more powers to the
Федерацию дали больше полномочий
federal
федеральному
center for example
центру например
powers of army f
полномочия армии ф
NT A in the European Union
НТ А в Европейском союзе национальные
each country has national armies each
армии есть у каждой страны каждо
state I just don't
государства Я просто не
know how it would be different if
знаю подго как было бы подругому если бы
for
к
example Well how to
примеру Ну как
say in Burti where the population is much
сказать в бурти где население намного
less than but even
меньше чемно даже
how there would be a national army
как бы там была национальная армия Из
How many people it would
скольки бы она людей
consist of this is just
состояла это просто
such a question I, I honestly I can't
вот вопрос такой я я я вот честно я не
imagine it no the point the point is not that How
представляю се нет суть суть не в том Из
many it would consist of The point is that these
скольки бы состоял Суть в том что эти
states Buryatia there Kalmykia
государства Бурятия там Калмыкия
Tatarstan And so on they agreed like this
Татарстана И так дальше они вот так
In ninety-second year
договорились В девяносто втором году да
and to delegate some powers to the
и делегировать какие-то полномочия
federal center as well as the
федеральному центру так же как
state of the European Union agreed and to
государство Евросоюза договорились и
delegate powers also made a
делегировать полномочия также сделали
single currency euro the state of the
единую валюту евро государство
Russian Federation made a single
Российской Федерации сделали единую
currency
валюту
ruble just you see well you were somehow
рубль просто видишь ну ты как-то так
surprised even in the Soviet Union eh 15
удивлялся даже и в Советском Союзе э 15
states each state  you had
государств у каждого государства был
your own Supreme
свой Верховный
Council also here is what is your
Совет также у вас вот как у вас орган
legislative body in Buryatia called
законодательный в бурятие называется
again the question should I repeat perhaps here is what is
ещё раз вопрос повторить пожалуй вот как
your legislative body called
у вас называется законодательный орган э
in
в
Buryatia in my opinion khural khural khural here
Бурятии по-моему хурал хурал хурал вот
you can look go to the website and
можешь посмотреть зайди на сайт и
see what a khural is
посмотри что такое хурал
here is the people's khural of the Republic of
вот народный хурал республики
Buryatia people's khural of the Republic of
Бурятия народный хурал республики
Buryatia Well it's like in Bashkiria kurultai Well yes
Бурятии Ну это как в Башкирии курултай
yes yes yes yes I know for sure but it's well well
Ну дадада дада вот я точно знаю но это
we had a kurultai in Bashkiria with
ну ну у нас курултай был в Башкирии с
what LTA Bashki this is not an official body
что лта башки это не официальный орган
this is when they gather just yes But this
это когда собираются просто да А вот
khural this is an official body
хурал вот этот в это официальный орган
Read this is the legislative body
Почитай это орган законодательной власти
above Read what is written there Go to
выше Прочитай как там написано Зайди на
its
его
website council committee people's khural
сайт совет комитета народного хурала
committee on budget tax finance on
комитета по бюджету налогом финансам по
state structure local
государственному устройству местному
self-government legality and issues of
самоуправлению законности и вопросам
state on social policy on
государственно по социальной политике по
land issues agrarian policy But
земельным вопросам аграрной политике Но
this is what the khural does so I
это чем хурал занимается так вот я тебе
opened it for you then look Yes here is the highest
открыл значит смотри Да вот высший
executive body of state
исполнительный орган государственной
power - this is the government of the republic
власти - это правительство республики
Buryatia and the legislative body of
Бурятия а законодательный орган
state power is the People's Khural of
государственной власти народный хурал
the Republic of Buryatia yes, that is, you as a
республики Бурятия да то есть у вас как
state have your own legislative
у государства есть свой законодательный
body your
орган свой
parliament it passes laws Yes,
парламент он принимает законы Да
the Republic of Buryatia
республики Бурятия
Well, yes, that is, well, you are a full-fledged
Ну да то есть ну вы полноценное
state just like Poland is a part of the
государство также как и Польша в составе
European Union, you are simply a part of the Russian
Евросоюза вы просто в составе Российской
Federation,
Федерации
but all the laws, in fact, as they
но все законы они по факту как они
come from the Central
исходят из Центрального
Administration, I will explain the same as in the European Union
управления объясню также как в Евросоюзе
Yes, there is national legislation in
Да есть национальное Законодательство в
Poland, there is Romania, so Dasha And there is a
Польше там Румынии так Даше А есть
pan-European one,
общеевропейская
they made it so that some laws
есть сделали так чтобы некоторые законы
were common, also in Russia there is a
они были общие также и в России есть
common Criminal Code, for example, yes
общий Уголовный кодекс например да А
And there is an
есть и
internal one Well, well, in principle, just like
внутренний Ну ну так же в принципе как и
in the USA,
в США там
each state has its own laws, there are
каждого у каждого штата свои законы там
a little different ones, but the essence is still the
немножко по-другому но суть всё равно
same in fact The essence is that Buryatia Yes,
одна по факту Суть в том что Бурятия Да
it Signed a federal treaty in the second year
она Подписала втором году федеральный
gave powers to the center, but it
договор дал в полномочия центру но также
can also withdraw from the Federal Treaty
может и выйти из Федерального договора
any country can withdraw from the Federal
любая страна может выйти из Федерального
Treaty it is simply a Union of different
договора это просто Союз разных
states Well, yes It's just that many Russians do
государств Ну да Просто многие россияне
not even understand Well, in what country do they
даже не понимают Ну в какой стране они
live I don't know, you have
живут Я не знаю вот у вас есть
law lessons at school Well  of course and
правоведение уроки в школе Ну конечно а
what did you study there not jurisprudence
что вы на них проходили не правоведение
social science not exactly jurisprudence but
обществознания не именно правоведение а
well law is also there where you
ну право тоже есть там где вы законы
study laws law we had law in
изучаете право право у нас было в
college
колледже
Yeah And you can see Well law starts with
Угу А ты видно Ну право начинается с
where you got it yeah that is you
дего к понял да да то есть ты после
went after the ninth grade yeah then look what you studied
девятого пошёл да то смотри что вы учили
in
на
jurisprudence
правоведении
laws Well how
законы Ну как
laws
законы
structure yeah that's the structure probably well
структуру угу вот структуру наверно ну
that is it turns out and you can't tell
то есть получается и вам не рассказать
cake Why why I studied in Bashkiria
торти Почему почему Я учился в Башкирии
back then and we were told that
ещ тогда и нам рассказывали то что у
Bashkortostan in general The
Башкортостана вообще У
first ones like in Bashkiria had a
первых как в Башкирии появилось
separate column here is this leaflet in the
отдельная графа вот это вот листочек в
passport where everything is written completely in Bashkir the
паспорте где полностью на башкирском всё
first ones had a gym
написано у первых появился гим
coat of arms and a president but then the truth is the lav
герб и президент но потом правда лаво
reb sde
реб сде
was Rust Khamitov and then for the sake of the
был Руст Хамитов вот а потом уже ради
Khabibovs he became the head of the head of the Republic Yes
хабиров стал главой главой Республики Да
that's it but I remember how in childhood we had a
вот но я помню как в детстве у нас был
president of the Republic of Bashkartastan Rustem
президент Республики башкартастан Рустем
Khamitov I remember this now Putin
Хамитов Это я помню это вот сейчас Путин
decreed Yes so that there would be no
постановил Да чтобы не было не
heads called presidents because
назывались главы президентами потому что
he doesn't like that the others also
он ему не нравится что остальные тоже
sound like presidents  And yes, but all this is
звучат президентами А так да но всё это
the head of the Republic, the head of state, I don’t
глава Республики глава государство не
know what they like and don’t like, but
знаю что там нравится что не нравится но
I remember exactly that My childhood was under
я точно помню что Моё детство было под
the president of the Republic of Bashkartastan But
президентом Республики башкартастан А
look, what do you think? Why is it that
вот смотри как ты считаешь Почему та же
Buryatia, in which you live, which
Бурятия Да в которой ты живёшь которая
has so many minerals,
имеет столько полезных ископаемых
so many natural resources, lives in
столько природных ресурсов да живёт
poverty? If I start talking now,
бедно Если я сейчас начну
Well, I’ll go far away and for a long time,
Ну уеду далеко и надолго
everyone tells me that, and no one has left because of
мне все так говорят ещё что-то никто от
this,
этого не
well, my personal opinion is that all the money
уехал ну лично моё мнение э все деньги
goes, well, that is, they go to Moscow,
они идут ну то есть они идут в Москву
everyone knows that all the
это все прекрасно знают по что все
money goes to
деньги идут в
Moscow. That is, like the
Москву То есть как бы
Republics, there are autonomous districts of
Республики там автономные округа
the region, they feed Moscow, one
края они кормят Москву один
Region. That’s why in Moscow, everyone lives
Регион Вот и поэтому в Москве Все живут
well, but outside of Moscow, the
хорошо а за пределами Москвы уже
harsh Russian reality is already beginning,
начинается суровая Российская реальность
so to speak, and even in the Moscow
так скажем причём даже в Московской
region, I will notice that the standard of living is already
области я замечу уже уровень жизни
much lower than in Moscow itself.
намного ниже чем в Москве самой
Well, on the one hand, it’s understandable, on the
Ну вообще оно с одной стороны понятно с
other, no. To be
другой нет Если
honest, when it was conceived as a
честно про когда задумывалась как
Federation, what is this, But a state
Федерация что ну это Бут государство
that will function
которые будет все функционировать и
normally, and then you see that they did everything to
нормально а потом видишь сделали что все
transfer all the flows to the Federal  center and
потоки перевели на Федеральный центр и
yes Yeah Well, okay, but how about people if
да Угу Ну а хорошо а как вот люди если
everyone understands I'm not talking to anyone
все понимают я вот с кем не разговариваю
Yes, everyone understands Yes, that Moscow takes
Да все понимают Да что Москва забирает
everything Moscow takes money, resources and
всё Москва забирает деньги ресурсы и
people returns only coffins in the best
людей возвращает только гробы в лучшем
case Yes, and people live like this for years
случае да и люди все вот так годами
and don't
живут и ничего не
change anything Do you believe that something can be changed
меняют веришь что можно изменить
Well, I'll answer like this Our box of
Ну ну я так отвечу у нас коробка
soda hasn't changed How long has it been and here to
соды не менялась Сколько уже а тут
change the box of soda do you mean the
изменить коробка сода это имеешь в виду
design is baking soda Yes, yes, it It
дизайн это пищевая сода Да да да он Он
only recently changed only
только недавно вот поменялся только
recently And then when they banned
недавно совсем И то когда запретили
digging up the Shikhans Well, then, then I was
раскапывать Ну вот тогда вот тогда я был
honestly, then I was for my fellow countrymen,
честно вот тогда я был за своих земляков
so to speak, stop, stop Are you talking about
так скажем стоп стоп Это ты про
Bashkartastan, probably? I
башкартастан наверное ещё
know about Kushtau It was Wow,
говоришь знаю про куштау было Вот это да
I was honestly then I was proud of my
я честно тогда я был горд за своих
fellow countrymen that they didn't let them, so to speak,
земляков то что не дали так скажем
kill the monument, a natural monument, so to
убить памятник природный памятник так
speak Well, yes, these are the guys who
скажем вот ну это да это эти кадры до
still walk there There were three
сих пор там ходят довольно было три
Shikhans, only
шихана остался
one remains I know for sure that this is the bottom of the
один это я точно знаю то что это дно
World Ocean, former I know this too
Мирового океана бывшее Это я тоже знаю
because we went there  what is there so to
потому что мы туда ездили то что там так
speak historical Heritage there Kapova
сказать историческое Наследие там капова
cave sites of ancient people I know Yes
пещера стоянки древних людей знаю Да это
I know all that Yes that's how and to kill all this
я всё знаю Да вот как бы и вот это всё
for the sake of some kind of soda well honestly
убивать ради соды какой-то ну честно вот
I myself would be unpleasant not Bashkor
мне бы самому было неприятно не башкор
handsome men it was then it was Still the
красавчики это тогда это был Ещё
Twentieth, I think somewhere around the year or d
Двадцатый по-моему где-то год или д
first d first water yes so seriously
первы д первы во да настолько серьёзно
all the people rose up defended the sacred
весь народ поднялся отстояли священные
Kushtau it was really commendable
куштау это было действительно похвально
yes Well
да Ну
yes that's exactly the question Yes I also
да это точно то такой вопрос Да я ещё
tell many Russians But if it
многим россиянам говорю А вот если так
happens that like the Soviet Union
случится что вот как Советский Союз же
collapsed and began to live as separate Republics
свалился и стали отдельной Республики
for example Estonia is small lives
жить например Эстония маленькая живёт
better than Russia
лучше чем живёт Россия
Yes how do people see if the
Да как люди видят если распадётся
Russian Federation disintegrates into separate
Российская Федерация на отдельные
states there is Bashkartastan Buryatia
государства там башкартастан Бурятия
Tatarstan there Primorsky Krai And so on
Татарстан там Приморский край И так
Yes what fears does this cause in
дальше Да какие страхи это вызывает у
people
людей
Well first
Ну первым
of all some national discord will begin
делом начнутся национальные какие-то
persecution will begin specifically against
розни вот начнётся гонение именно вот на
Russians that's it
русских вот
I know for sure I
э вот это вот я точно знаю
understand for sure
то точно понимаю потому
because Bashkir nationalists Well I say
что башкирские националисты Ну я говорю
I am the Supreme Commander  life almost lived in
я ВС жизнь почти прожи
Bastani Bashkir nationalists They are
бастане башкирские националисты Они они
worse than Russian
хлеще русских
nationalists Here they are Well, to be honest,
националистов Вот и они Ну вот честно
they smile in your face, they are
скажу они вот в лицо
just waiting for the moment,
улыбаются просто ждут момент
what are they under there, I honestly
под чем они там находятся я вот честно
don’t
не
know, but if something happens, the
знаю но в случае
very first ones who get caught, so to
чего самые первые кто попадётся так
speak, in the heat of the moment, are Russians Well,
скажем под горячую руку это русские Ну
yes, just like in many other
да так же как и во многих других
Asian republics,
республиках Азии было
yes Well, in Tatarstan I know for sure that
да Ну вот в Татарстане Я точно знаю что
no, this will not happen, even if and how can I
нет такого не будет если даже и как
say, uh,
сказать ээ
if this happens, then in Tatarstan
если такое случится то в Татарстане
this will not happen, I know for sure, I
такого не будет это я точно знаю это я
can say with confidence, Burya Buryatia,
могу сказать с уверенностью буря Бурятии
the same thing, Buryati in Buryati,
тоже самое буряти в буряти просто
there are just about 20 percent of Buryats, only well, so to
бурятов где-то процентов 20 только ну
speak, simply in
так скажем просто в
Buryatia Well, how can I
Бурятии Ну как
say All this is just a fairy tale, that
сказать Вот это всё просто сказки то что
they ban nationality They ban languages,
запрещают национальное Запрещают языки
that is, they put them at the forefront, but no, for
то есть там ставят во главу но нет к
example, in Bashkiria there are Bashkir
примеру в Башкирии есть башкирские
gymnasiums, Bashkir lyceums Well, there, with an
гимназии башкирские лицеи Ну там с
emphasis on the Bashkir language, there are also
уклоном на башкирский язык э также есть
Tatar ones  Chuvash Well, in principle, the
татарские чувашские Ну полно в принципе
same thing here in Buryatia, here we have a
также и здесь в Бурятии вот у нас есть в
Tatar lyceum in Buryatia, a
Бурятии татарский лицей в Бурятии
Tatar lyceum,
татарский лицей
here no one forbids anyone to
вот никто никому не запрещает здесь
speak the Buryat language, that is,
разговаривать на бурятском языке то есть
well,
ну
I know one thing for sure here, only in
здесь одно точно знаю только вот в
Bashkiria it will be only in Bashkiria there will be
Башкирии будет только в Башкирии будет
something like this,
что-то вот такое
but with others, it is also possible that in Tva there
вот но с други Вот ещё возможно в тве
will be, well, in Tva there are almost no Russians, therefore,
будет ну в тве русских почти нет поэтому
and Well, well, anyway, some part of it, It
и Ну ну всё равно какая-то часть Вот
will be found in Yakutia, the same thing will happen,
попадётся и В Якутии тоже самое будет
I know for sure, in Yakutia Yes, Sakha, if we
это я точно знаю В Якутии Да Саха если
look at it this way, during the Soviet Union, the
так посмотрим во время Советского Союза
Sakha Republic was inhabited by
Республика Саха на водня
visiting elements, Ukrainians, Russians, and
приезжим элементом украинцами русскими и
so on, and in Perm, there were
так дальше и в Перм году Сха было там
30% of them there, but
30% толь сейчас уже
now in the Sakha Republic there are more than
сейчас в Республике Саха якутов больше
50% of Yakuts, that is, Russians are leaving, Russians are not
50% то есть русские уезжают русские не
reproducing Well, first of all,
размножаются Ну они ну во-первых
objectively, there is nothing to do there,
объективно там делать
That is, when I serve in
нечего То есть когда я Служи в
the army, I
армии я
once They say We sign a contract,
раз Они говорят Мы контракт подписываем
I say And what, why, like, no grandmothers are waiting at home, they
я говорю А что зачем типа дома не ждут
say Well  firstly, there is
бабки о говорят Ну во-первых в Якутии
nothing to do in Yakutia, secondly, there is an
типа делать нечего во-вторых тут есть
opportunity to
типа возможность
earn money here,
заработать Ну и всё И вот вот так вот
Well, that's it. And that's how it is, yes, therefore, A is good. Well,
да поэтому А хорошо Ну вот по конфликтам
I understood the fears regarding the conflicts. Are there any fears that
я понял страхи А есть ли страхи что вот
these Republics will not be able to survive
эти Республики не смогут выжить
on their own? Yes, of course, but how is
самостоятельно Да конечно
that possible? I wonder. Yes, Russians have two things in their heads. The first is that Moscow takes all the money, and the second is that we cannot survive without Moscow. Well, in what sense then? Not only without Moscow, but in fact. Yes, without Moscow, in the sense that although Moscow
Москвы в том плане то что хоть Москва
takes everything, it still somehow
всё и забирает но всё равно она как-то
feeds us, or what? I don't know how to explain this. I do
кормит что ли Я не знаю это объяснить Я
n't know how to do it.
не знаю как обя
This thought is just on the tip of my tongue. I'm
просто на языке крутится эта мысля я
trying to say, just look, if
пытаюсь вот сказать просто смотри если
it takes, say,
она забирает там
100 rubles and gives back 20, then it is not it that
условно 100 руб а отдаёт 20 то это не
feeds us. It took 80. Well, in
она кормит Это она забрала 80 ну по
fact, yes, that is, if you just don't give it
факту да то есть если просто не отдавать
to Moscow and feed yourself with the same money,
в Москве а на те же деньги кормиться
what is the
самим в чём
problem? Then that's another
проблема тогда уже другой
question. This is where I'm getting at.
вопрос просто я к чему веду
When I communicate with different
вот когда общаюсь с разными
representatives of different peoples of different
представителями разных народов разных
republics, many people, because of the fact that there
республик многие из-за того что Ну не
was no example of their own.  Independence they do not
было примера своей Независимости они не
understand how this state
понимают как это государство вообще
can function at all yes that is, many
может функционировать да то есть многие
for example from the same Tatarstan
например из того же Татарстана
Bashkortostan if you ask there they are
Башкортостана если там спрашиваешь они
like Damn, how are we supposed to live
такие Блин а как как мы типа будем жить
with whom to trade that is, there is no such
с кем торговать то есть нету этого
image of these people
образа это людей Да
Yes it scares well the Armed Forces are early How can I
страшит ну ВС рано Как
say even if this happens
сказать если даже такое случится
then sooner or later the Republics will still
то рано или поздно Республики всё равно
learn to do this Absolutely right
научатся этим заниматься Абсолютно верно
also this will be sooner it will be sooner
также это это будет рано это будет рано
or later I don’t know when this will be I
или поздно не знаю когда это будет
can’t even imagine Well I’m
Вот не могу представить даже вот Ну я
just getting to where I’m getting at I think I have a
просто к чему веду Я считаю у меня такая
theory that
теория есть что
after the First World War they collapsed well
после Первой мировой войны развали ну
history is cyclical I don’t mean I’m not talking about
история циклична я я по не я не про
cyclicality empires collapsed like this
цикличность разваливались империи так
Arsk collapsed Ottoman collapsed
Арская развалилась Османская развалилась
and a bunch of different states appeared
и куча разных государств появилась
Russian collapsed new
Российская развалилась появились новые
states appeared then Lenin
государства потом Ленин немного
reassembled it a little in the form of the Soviet Union In
пересобрал её в виде Советского Союза В
1991 the
девяносто первом году развалился
Soviet Union collapsed this is like a continuation of the
Советский Союз это как продолжение
collapse of the Russian Empire and now
распада Российской Империи и сейчас
there is still the Russian Federation
осталась ещё вот Российская Федерация
as well as from different these countries of different
как тоже из разных вот этих стран разных
subjects of different peoples of different regions
субъектов разных народов разных регионов
and somewhere logically approaches the third
и где-то подходит к по логике третий
stage of the collapse of the Russian  Empires here is the
этап распада Российской Империи вот
final one on uh here is the state from the
окончательный на ээ вот э государство из
Russian Federation plus This will not
Российской Федерации плюс Это же не
only be a collapse by uh
только будет распад по ээ республикам
national republics For example, if we take the
национальным Например если мы возьмём
Far East Yes, Russians live there
Дальний Восток Да там живут русские
Russian-speaking, but for Moscow and Moscow
русскоязычные но они для Москвы и Москва
for them - it's a different world,
для них - это другой мир
if we look at the Spanish
вот если мы посмотрим когда-то испанский
world once, there was Spain and there were colonies in
мир вот была Испания и были колонии в
South America Yeah, now they are all
Южной Америке Угу сейчас они все
independent states there Cuba speaks
независимые государства там Куба говорит
Spanish Chile speaks Spanish
по-испански Чили говорит по-испански
Argentina speaks Spanish And so on, but
Аргентина по-испански И так дальше но
each independent country and also uh,
каждая независимая страна и также ээ вот
conditionally the same Primorsky Krai that
условно тот же Приморский край что его
connects it with Moscow I communicate with
связывает с Москвой я вот так общаюсь с
the guys from Primorsky like this, they all drive
ребятами с Приморского они все ездят на
right-hand drive cars, they have been to Japan
праворульных тачках они бывали в Японии
and China more often than to Moscow, they have definitely
в Китае чаще чем в Москве они там точно
been there And almost none of them
бывали А в Москве Почти никто из них не
have been to Moscow because this
бывал потому что это
uh I will say so well because firstly,
э я скажу так ну потому что во-первых по
logistically it is much easier, that is,
логистике это проще намного то есть
to get there conditionally from some
добраться условно из какого-нибудь
Usuriyskaya Well, it is a Chinese city, you
усурийская Ну это китайский город
can get there by minibus Yes, here is the same Primorsky Krai that connects it with Moscow
добраться там можно на маршрутке Да вот
Vladivostok can
э с Владивостока можно и на море
be visited by the sea in Vladivostok, in fact, I
побывать во Владивостоке можно по факту
don’t remember whether it borders China or not.
не помню граничит ли он с Китаем или нет
There is
Там же есть
Vladivostok there, I don’t know if it borders, but
там Владивосток не знаю или граничит но
there is a border somewhere. Well, I remember for sure that
там где-то граница есть Ну вот я точно
Suris has a border. I
помню то что у сурис есть граница Вот
think it is located either in Nakhodka
она по-моему находится либо в Находке
or in Artem. Well, in
либо в Артёме Ну в
the city of Nakhodka, it is by the
городе Находка она на
sea, yes. Nakhodka on Moreno is
море раз да Находка на Морено
much simpler. And
намного проще Да и
then, all its life,
потом всю как бы жизнь
Primorye lived off Asia, roughly speaking,
Приморье жило за счёт Азии грубо говоря
that is, Japanese, Korean,
то есть японские корейские Тачки
Chinese, Korean, Japanese cars. Cola in
китайская корейская японская Кола в
Adidas stores, Fisherman, Nike, all
магазинах Adidas рибак Nike все
discount cards don’t work. Western ones
дисконтные карты не работают западные
work. Only Asian ones work. And
работают только азиатские и до сих пор
they continue to work there to this day. I know this for sure.
они там продолжают работать это я точно
In principle, in principle. They lived well
в принципе в принципе Они прекрасно жили
before all the events, yes. And now they live exactly the
и до всех событий да А сейчас они живут
same. Well, I’ll scan the prices, but how can I
ровно так же Ну что Ну цены скану но как
tell if there is availability, if there are goods on the
сказать наличие наличие товаров на
shelves? Well, the availability of
прилавках Ну не изменилось наличие
cars hasn’t changed either. On the contrary, what’s
автомобилей тоже не изменилось наоборот
most
даже что самое
interesting is that they even bring new cars, that
интересное привозят даже новые машины то
is, they buy them out. They bring them at auctions in
есть выкупают На торгах в
Japan.  That is, for the first time in my
Японии привозят То есть я впервые в
life I saw a Crown Toyota Crown
жизни вообще увидел Краун Toyota Crown
for the first time in my life At an auction This
впервые в жиз На торгах Это имеется в
means wrecked Yes cars Well, somewhere wrecked
виду битые Да машины Ну где-то битый
somewhere Just there I don’t know Well the guy
где-то Просто там я не знаю Ну чувак
was riding and riding and got tired He just, well,
катался катался ну надоело Ему просто ну
there he threw it in the impound lot they took everything and
там кинул на штрафстоянку забрали всё и
he didn’t buy it back or they fined him there I
он её не выкупил либо оштрафовали там я
don’t know Well, all sorts of things happen That’s what I’m
не знаю ну всякое же бывает разное Вот я
saying is that for the first time in my life I
говорю то что ну впервые в жизни я
saw a Crown exactly in
вообще увидел Краун именно вот ээ в
Primorye I was in Moscow And in
Приморье Я и в Москве был И в
St. Petersburg, that is,
санкт-петербурге то есть
all the same, somehow it’s better that
э всё равно как-то лучше как будто живёт
Primorye lives That’s because there are a lot of young people there
Приморье Вот потому что там и молодёжи
and the infrastructure is very well developed and
и инфраструктура очень хорошо развита и
tourism too, and
туризм тоже причём
international tourism That is, if we
международный туризм То есть если
say to
условно в
Moscow Well, also, how can I say, they fly from
Москву Ну тоже как сказать летят с
different corners of the planet, so to speak, well,
разных так сказать уголков планеты вот
just to
ну просто
look and it’s like, well, it’s normal
посмотреть и это как ну ну это нормально
it’s the capital But here, it’s not the
это столица А тут вроде не
capital, it’s like the city is roughly
столица вроде город грубо говоря
located in the world in fact, if you think about it that way,
находится мира по факту если так
but people
рассуждать но туда люди
go there and people of other nationalities go there
едут и других национальностей едут туда
That’s why  Vladivostok
люди Вот и поэтому Владивосток Очень
Lives very well in fact Well, and what's
неплохо живёт на самом деле Ну и тем
more, this city is called the city of
более этот город называется городом
youth and there really is, that is,
молодёжи и там действительно так то есть
there is some kind of old
там именно вот какого-то старого
population there are few elderly people, on the contrary, there are
населения там пожилых людей их мало
more
наоборот больше
young people Just for these right-hand drive
молодёжи Как раз за этими праворукая
cars Yes, with a right-hand drive Well,
тачками Да с праворукой
yes, because I also ask many from there
да потому что я тоже да многих оттуда
were in Moscow no were in
спрашиваю были в Москве нет были в
Moscow no in China Japan yes yes yes
Москве нет в Китае Японии да да да
yes China for them in general how is it like
да Китай у них вообще как это как к
going out to a neighbor Well, yes, I'm saying that you
соседу выйти Ну это да я говорю то есть
can get to Harbin by minibus and
до Харбина можно на маршрутке доехать а
to And how long is it from there It will take about
до И сколько там это Это займёт примерно
five hours by
ну часов пять езды на
bus It's a different country in fact, this is well,
автобусе Это другая страна по факту это
this is all This is already a different country And here
ну это всё Это уже другая страна А тут
in your country you
ты в своей стране
have to fly on a plane for
должен лететь на самолёте за
fabulous
баснословные
money in order to what, to look at the
бабки чтобы что чтобы посмотреть на
Kremlin, Moscow
Кремль на Москва
City and even the Kremlin Well, you can't
Сити и то на Кремль Ну в Кремль не
always get to the Kremlin, Red Square,
всегда можно попасть на Красную Площадь
but to the Sea of ​​Japan, yes, even go every
вот а на Японское море да хоть Каждый
day
день
Well, I think that money
вот я считаю то что вот бабки как раз
needs to be
таки нужно именно в Приморье
poured out in Primorye because, roughly speaking, there are one and a
выливать потому что грубо говоря там
half billion nearby and
сколько полтора миллиарда под боком и
everyone goes  they leave all their money and
все едут все свои деньги оставляют а
tourism is poorly developed in
туризм слабо развит на самом
fact But look, your people don't
деле А смотри вот люди у вас не
think about the fact that because of the war, a
задумаются над тем что из-за войны
huge amount of money that could have
огромное количество денег которые могли
gone into developing infrastructure went
пойти в обустройство инфраструктуры ушло
to the
на
war, it wouldn't have gone to developing the infrastructure
войну оно бы и не ушло на устройство на
But where would it have gone? I don't
устройство А куда бы оно ушло А я не
know where it would have gone, where it's been going all my life
знаю куда бы ушло куда всю жизнь уходило
Well, to be honest,
Ну вот честно
we didn't live well before the war,
сказать мы до войны Не жили
and during it too That is, we didn't
хорошо ну и во время тоже То есть Не
live rich to begin with, that is, that's how it is, it's
жили богаты начинать то есть вот так
interesting somehow, yes Well, that's
вот интересно как-то да Ну вот так вот
how it
так оно и
is Well, that
есть Ну то
is, to say, but a teacher's salary I
есть сказать но зарплата у учителя Я
know
знаю
Buryats there is 25,000 the average salary and from
буряти там 25.000 средняя зарплата и из
that you have to pay personal income tax they even
них ты должен заплатить НДФЛ его ещё
raised it this year from that you have to
подняли в этом году из них ты должен
pay utility bills if
заплатить коммунальную услуги если у
you have a child You also have to Well, if he is
тебя ребёнок Ты должен ещё Ну если он
naturally small, there is a small one, there is
естественно маленький там небольшой там
a sixteen-year-old, there is a seventeen-year-old,
шестнадцатилетний там семнадцатилетний
that is, he can't
ну то есть работать не может
go to work, you still have to
пойти ты ещ его должен
support him, but you can't survive on that salary
содержать но на эту зарплату не выжить
No matter how hard you try That's why you
Как бы ты не старался Поэтому ты
get out loans, debts, a mortgage, and that's
вылезаешь кредиты долги в ипотеку и то
25,000 rubles  in today's reality Well, it's
25.000 руб в нынешних реалиях Ну это
even 250 dollars Yes, it's funny, it's well,
даже 250 долларов Да это смешно это это
how can I say it's not even a
ну даже как сказать это даже не платёж
mortgage payment No, of course You can take
ипотеке Нет конечно Ты можешь там взять
a one-room apartment there But how will you live with your family in
однушку Но как ты будешь семьёй в
a one-room apartment
однушке
You can take a one-room apartment and pay
жить Ты можешь взять однушку и платить
20,000 there, in my opinion
20.000 по-моему
And what to eat And what is there Well, your
А что кушать А что есть Ну вот у тебя
salary is 25,000 Yes, you still have to pay personal income tax from
зарплата 25000 Да у тебя ещё НДФЛ уходит
it Although, in my opinion, there are no teachers already
с неё Хотя нет по-моему учителей уже уже
after f Yes, in hand Well, you still
после ф Да на руки Вот ну тебе ещё
have to pay utilities in
коммуналку надо заплатить по
fact Well,
факту Ну
And now And now, as they say,
вот А сечас А сейчас как говорят
salaries have increased in fact, no way at all
зарплаты подняли по факту вобще никак
I'm the only one I studied to be a
я вот единственное вот я отучился на
teacher as a physical
педагога на преподавателя физической
education teacher Yeah, yeah, I went to school
культуры Угу э я пошёл в школу
to get a job they said the salary was
устраиваться сказали зарплата
30,000 I looked at the living conditions, so to
30.000 Я посмотрел на условия жизни так
speak, this was before the army I looked
скажем это ещё до армии было я посмотрел
at the living conditions in the Republic of
на условия жизни в Республике
Bashkartastan 30,000 it's laughter it's
башкартастан 30.000 это смех это
tears and I went to work as a
слёзы и я пошёл работать
fitness instructor
фитнес-инструктором
and it's just that
и именно вот как раз-таки
private individuals get paid twice as much  or even three
частники получают в два а то и в три а
or even four times more Well, for
то и в четыре раза больше Ну вот к
example, a schedule of 5 above,
примеру график 5 над
conditionally, at school,
условно в школе
and 25,000, well,
и 25.000 ну
30, or you have a schedule of 3 to 3 in a
30 либо же у тебя график 3 на3 в
fitness center
фитнес-центре
and a salary in fact, from all of them there are
и зарплата по факту из всех там личные
some personal classes, then just a rate, for
занятия какие-то потом просто ставка к
example, a trainer from a fitness club, a
пример тренера от фитнес-клуба
fixed salary, but in principle it
фиксированный оклад но оно в принципе
is also
ещё и группу людей потом есть
possible to recruit a group of people, in principle, if you
возможность набрать в принципе если вот
add everything up like this You get about
так вот всё сложить У тебя выходит около
110 and that's it already Yes, that's already
110 и вот это уже Да это уже
my payment for housing and communal services to
мого плату ЖКХ на
pay Well, utilities, housing and communal services to pay for a
оплату Ну коммуналка ЖКХ на оплату
mortgage, food, water, that's all and maybe a
ипотеки еды воды вот этого всего и может
little bit of all that will
чуть-чуть
remain
останется
So you went to the elections No,
Вот ты на выборы
you don't believe it Well, it's not that I don't believe it, I just
веришь Ну я не то что не верю я просто
understand What will they be like there was no
понимаю Какой ихо будет не было
choice Well,
выбора Ну а
why, here's my personal civic
зачем вот моя лично вот гражданская
position, I don't go to
позиция я не хожу на
elections, especially since they sang about market
выборы тем более как пели рыночные
relations, I don't go to elections, I
отношения я не хожу на выборы я никому
don't
не
trust anyone Well, at least I went to city municipal elections
верю вот А хоть на городские выборы
No That is, even like a depu And you're
ходил Нет То есть даже типа депу А ты
simply not registered  where you live well
прописан просто не там где живёшь да ну
no I am a citizen of Russia I can in
нет Я же гражданин России Я могу по
fact vote everywhere
факту везде голосовать име
you can only vote where no no no no no no well
ты же можешь только там где нет нет нет
or Yes for a city No for a
ну или Да за городского Нет за
city can only those who are
городского могут только те кто
registered there in the
прописанные там в
city That is, if you are registered there in
городе То есть если прописан там в
Chuvashia or in Bashkortostan then you
Чуваши или в Башкортостане то ты за того
can vote for that deputy Well yes then
депутата можешь голосовать Ну да тогда
you don't care Well that is well well and
тебе всё равно Ну то есть ну ну и тем
especially since all our heads of the Republic
более как бы у нас все главы Республики
are from United Russia from the United Russia party
они от Единой России от партии Единой
and there too the choice is in fact small If you
и там тоже выбор по факту невелик Если
think about it Well for example Here is the
так подумать Ну вот к примеру Вот это
most very stupid action for
самая очень такая глупая акция за
which I was very
которую Мне очень было
ashamed This is the fact that government
стыдно Это то что государственные
agencies forced their employees to
учреждения заставляли своих работников
post photos from the elections there
там выкладывать фотографии с выборов
like I voted for such and
типа вот я проголосовала за того-то
such or I voted for such and such and
того-то или Я проголосовал за того-то
such here my choice there is not biased at all
того-то вот мой выбор совсем там не
This is well this is so to
предвзятый Вот это ну это очень так
speak flawed in fact this is an
скажем ущербно на самом деле это
open fact it is on the Internet
открытый факт это есть в интернете как
like all these posts they
бы вот и все эти посты они в интернете
are still on the Internet But this is such a
до сих пор находятся Но это вот такая
how to
вот как
say very shameful shameful action  it was
сказать очень стыдно стыдная акция была
very shameful, that is, in fact, people were
очень стыдная то есть по факту людям
roughly speaking shoved in the face by the fact that there is
грубо говоря тыкали в морду тем то что
no choice. You either vote for this
Выбора нет Ты либо за этого голосуешь
or Well, it's not the only thing that's also interesting is the
Либо Ну не едино вот тоже интересно
phenomenon of these school
феномен вот эти это школьные вот эти
teachers who are
учителя которым которы
25,000 rubles 250 dollars yes For your
25000 руб 250 долларов да Для вашего
region, yes, it's funny and they are also
региона это да смешно и их ещё и
forced there, I don't know, under threat of
заставляют там не знаю под страхом
dismissal or what to do, these
увольнения или что делать вот эти
shameful things and they do instead of
постыдные вещи и они делают вместо того
quitting and going somewhere as a
чтобы уволиться и пойти где-то
tutor and then Well, because there is
репетитором и дальше Ну потому что
no demand for tutors or anyone,
спроса нет ни на репетиторов ни на кого
people
у людей ту денег
don't have money, and if they have money, then they have
нет а если есть деньги то у них уже
n't gone to school as a
не пошл в школу физкультурника А пошл
physical education teacher for a long time. But they went as a fitness trainer
фитнес-тренером
yes yes, and some other physical education teacher at
да да а другой какой-то физкультурник в
school came out crying that I
школе выходил с тем плакати что Я
voted
проголосовал
Well, it also depends on age. I am a
Ну там ведь тоже от возраста зависит Я
young specialist. I can be taught
молодой специалист меня можно научить
there. I would have even more energy,
там я как бы у меня энергии ещё побольше
but here they simply objectively
будет а тут они просто объективно
assess the situation. Firstly, they
ситуацию оценивают у них во-первых стаж
have already worked a lot at this school.
в этой школе отработан уже большой
Secondly, if they are UVO, where will they go?  with
во-вторых если они УВО куда они пойдут с
this experience they will not be needed they have no
этим стажем они не нужны будут у них ни
energy nothing it is useless to
энергии ничего нету их бесполезно
train them Well, let's say for
обучать Ну вот условно Да вот я вот к
example I came to the fitness center Well, a
примеру пришёл в фитнес-центр Ну вот
young athlete came, that is, a candidate for master of sports under
пришёл молодой спортсмен то есть КМС под
ZDO and all that, he came to get a job and also
Здо все дела пришёл устраиваться и также
came a pot-bellied physical education teacher who
пришёл пузатый Физрук который 30 лет в
fenced off someone at school for 30 years They will take Well,
школе отгородил кого Они возьмут Ну
naturally They will take a young candidate for master of sports they will not take a
естественно Они возьмут молодого КМС они
pot-bellied physical education teacher
не возьмут пузатого физрука
simply because he has experience they will
просто потому что у него стаж есть они
not take them they will not do this
не возьмут они этого не сделают потому
because firstly there are big risks after
что во-первых есть большие риски
all adults They get sick more often in
всё-таки взрослые люди Они болеют чаще у
adults adult problems And a
взрослых людей взрослые проблемы А
young person, what is young, his body is still
молодой что молодой у него организм ещё
healthy That is, he has problems yet There are
здоровый То есть у него проблем ещё пока
no such things there is a family children that's
Таких вот нету там семья дети вот это
there I don't know about loans
там я не знаю п кредитов
and I don't know life in debt for a young person like that, that
и не знаю жиз в долгах у молодого такого
is, there will be no problems with
не то есть проблем никаких не будет с
him And if he also served in the army, that's
ним А если ещё и в армии отслужил это
generally well, well, as a Plus That is, I won't
вообще ну как бы Плюс То есть его не
pull him there in the middle of the year like here's your
дёрну там посреди года типа вот тебе
summons that's it You are obliged to go and serve that's it
повестка всё Ты обязан идти служить всё
This is a huge plus and that is, naturally they will take a
Это огромный плюс и то есть возьмут
young person and therefore Well, people  they
естественно молодого и поэтому Ну люди
just don't want to lose their job they
просто место работы терять не хотят они
just understand that later no
просто понимают то что они потом уже
one will need them that is, in fact, that is
никому не нужны будут то есть по сути
why they receive a salary
они поэтому и получают зарплату потому
because no one needs them even the state,
что они никому не нужны даже государству
by and large
получается по большому счёту
Well, if you look at it that way, then
Ну если так расценивать то
yes Well, why am I saying this Because
да Ну почему это говорю Потому что у
my
меня
grandmother
бабушка
is a physics teacher, she worked as a
она преподаватель физики она работала
teacher at a
учителем в школе в
physics school So what does she get now, a
физике Ну и что она сейчас получает
pension of 14,000 dollars Well, that is
пенсию 140 долларов Да ну это это это
not normal,
ненормально
especially since the utilities issue, did the grandmother
тем более коммуналка вопрос бабушка на
go to the polls No, she doesn't
выборы ходила Нет она тоже не
go either There are grandmothers who
ходит есть такие бабушки которые
get it, go to the polls, vote for the
получают ходят на выборы голосуют за
government Well, that's not the point, grandmother
власть Ну не дело не в этом бабушка У
Mine hasn't gone to the polls since the collapse of the Union,
меня она ещё с развала Союза не ходила
that is, in the Soviet Union,
на выборы а то есть в Советском Союзе
as soon as she turned
как ей только вот исполнилось
18 She went to the polls in the Soviet Union
18 Вот она ходи в Советском Союзе на
without a choice, she went, that's also
выборы без выбора она ходила вот тоже
interesting Look, don't you think that the fact
интересно Смотри не считаешь ли ты то
that your grandmother didn't go to the polls after the collapse of
что твоя бабушка не ходила после развала
the Union, she didn't go to the polls, that is why she
Союза не ходила на выборы она поэтому и
now has 14,000 rubles because she
имеет теперь 14.000 руб потому что она
had someone and how to lead her
ей было кто и как будет руководить
state and so
государством и так
on
дальше
Well she lived
Ну она жила
well until a couple of years until my grandfather
хорошо до пары до времени пока дедушки
passed away because my grandfather was a
не стало потому что дед у меня был
military man may he rest in peace Well he died
военный царство ему небесное он Ну умер
of diabetes not because he was in the war
от диабета не от того что там на войне
he died of diabetes naturally Well a
он умер от диабета естественно Ну пенсию
person no longer receives a pension he doesn't exist So they
человек больше не получает его нету Вот
lived on their grandfather's pension my grandfather had a very
и жили на пенсию деда у деда была очень
good pension very decent That is
хорошая пенсия очень приличная То есть
even in my opinion a little more than
даже по-моему чуть больше чем зарплата у
my mother's salary just for the fact that he sits at
моей мамы вот просто за то что он сидит
home well and plus he received an apartment from the
дома ну и плюсом квартиру получил от
state so let's say he
государства вот так скажем в последний
managed to jump on the last train
вагон успел запрыгнуть
Well and my grandmother lived very well therefore
Ну и бабушка жила очень хорошо поэтому е
if I say so it was all the same
если так выразится было по барабану вот
And the child went to the elections didn't go I don't know
А дет на выборы ходил не ходил я не знаю
Well that is yes well The point is what it turns out
Ну то есть да ну Суть в чём получается
that the grandmother is there 30 years old Yes she
что бабушка эти там 30 лет Да она
goes out
выходит
She didn't care what was going on with the
Вот ей было всё равно что там с
state Yes in fact she is not an
государством Да по сути она не
elector whoever will be will be and there were a lot of such
избира кто будет то будет и таких куча
grandmothers conditionally grandmothers
бабушек было условно бабушек
guys and girls Yes who
парней также и девчонок Да которым
had and it turns out and now all these people have forgotten
было и получается и теперь все эти люди
to clean up
расхлёбывать
the mess Well what else can I say it's
забили Ну а что ещё сказать-то
logical it was just interesting yes Or are you
логично просто интересно было да Или ты
this  you understand
это понимаешь
yes Okay I'll go okay let's do
да Ладно пойду я хорошо давай
this all Ukrainian grandmothers grandfathers
так все украинские бабушки дедушки
youth end the war and there will be elections and there
молодь вийна закинчить и выборы будуть и
will be elections more than once from the Supreme Court T who says There is
выборы будуть не раз от ВС Т хто каже Та
no need to go to the elections and what is there that
не треба ходити на вибори та что там той
vibration All the same nothing all the same everything is
вибр Всё равно ничего всё равно всё За
true for us And what is the voice that inspires Yes you
нас вирно А что й голос впливае Да ви
will then be on the elders Like this grandmother
будете Тод на старост Як оця бабушка
and
и
I sit now T grandmothers I will now
сидити я зараз Т бабушки я зараз
tell that everything is so bad
розказують что вот всё я так погано
pension is small this T grandmothers I am 30 years old or did not
пенсия мала це Т бабушки я 30 ров або не
go to the elections or voted for
ходили на вибори або голосували за
someone
якихось
about That there will be a choice Yes To be a citizen
про Тому Бути выбор Да Бути громадянином
- this is a great
- це велика
visibility But you yourself are at the elections Yes in the
видповидальнисть Але саме Вы на выборах
elections Yes the form of the
Да в тому чис на выборах Да форму
future of our country is not just a country as I
майбутне свое краины не просто краины як
believe but in myself in the country and this is very
якоюсь а себе в й крани да и це дуже
important father fish I want  to convey to all Ukrainians
важливо оцей фиш Я хочу до всх украинв
Yes, elections will take place, war
донести Да вибори будуть пройде вийна
will take place, elections will take place,
будуть выборы
parliament, presidential elections, go to
мисце парламент президентски ходить на
elections, go to elections, make a choice,
выборы ходить на выборы робить выбор
sensibly, join in supporting these
осмысленно включайтесь в пидтримку тих
political forces, I see, yes, because
политичних сил я ви трите да тому що у
we have many Ukrainians
нас багато украинв
in the elections How to get money for
на выборах Як залучаються за бабки
standing in line for submitting newspapers Yes, most
постоя в намет подава газеты Да
Ukrainians take part in elections How
бильшисть украинв с приймае вибори Як
can you make some money there
можливисть там о зробити якогось Бабла
For example, there is much more there for an agitator
агитатора наприклад там чи ще
And in America, for example Yes, because
щось А в Амери наприклад Да навпаки что
people have parties Yes, people eat agitation
люди тримають парти Да люди едять агиту
for a party, it is amazing with us, yes, we have little
за парти у нас дивно да у нас льки Дея
Party activities, so that people gave up a penny for them or
парти та що люди на них сдались грош або
people
люди
stood in line for a party for free,
безкоштовно стояли в наметах за партии
this is an idea of ​​a party, if people do not prepare for a party
це идей парти якщо за партию люди не
without money,
готови без бабок
agitation Yes, it means this is a party  not for people
агива Да значит це партия не для людей
this Party is for people ready people
це Партия для яко люди гото люди
understand and this is how I will stand for
понимают а це якась фи Я постою льки за
money here on the tent and other kind of newspapers
бабки тут на намет и ВН рода ти газеты
Yes When you understand that this party is people
Да Коли вы розумиете що ця партия люди
Yes it will serve your interests if you
Да видповидае вашим интересам якщо йс ви
understand this then you will be ready
це розумиете да то ви будете готови
to realize interests and otherwise there
реализовать интереси а инакше инакше
will be great gshoshki to put up their
будуть велики гшо шки розставляти своих
candidates Yes pay agitators and they
кандидат Да платити агитатора и вони
will always
будуть завжди
win always win someone will
вигравати завжди вигравати хтось буде за
buy for buckwheat and so
гречку купувати так
on Sweet theme of election of
дальше Слад тема выбо
vibs is not required and in election because
вибов не треба тка и ВД вибору тому що
vibr vibr
вибр вибр
is taking the role of the
це взяття видповидальности на себе за
country of Russia as it is not my fault I can
краину це росия ка я не виноват я могу
do Yes every Ukrainian is guilty to
сделать Да кожен украинец повинен
speak yes yes in me in that number many
говорити да да в мене в тому чис багато
that  lie down and I am guilty brother tsyu far
що залежить и я повинен брати цю вдаль
on myself like squeak comment Slava
на себе лайк писка комент Слава
ukrai write on y Telegram right now axis
украи пись на й Telegram прям зараз ось
VN
ВН
apok this is very and very important YouTube is busy with
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
us through scarg ORV in your ban and very
нас через скарг ОРВ в твый бан и дуже
many videos I do not show people at times do not
багато видео не показую людям вчасно не
show information about streams That is
показуе информация про стрими Тому для
why we Mali operational links
того щоб ми Мали оперативний звязок
are written right now and while there in telegram
пишиться прямо зараз а пок там в телегра
okrim video there is also useful information
окрим видео ще теж ва корисна информация
and we are obliged to you trimati constant
и мы повинни з вами тримати постийний
operational links
оперативный звязок
independently in that chi will show you the process
незалежно в того чи покаже вам проце
YouTube Slava ukraine
YouTube Слава украини
subscribe N
подпишись N